Finding Aid for the Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education Records LSC.1923
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Minutes, 1875-2009
  - Los Angeles Unified School District, 1875 May 19-2009 June 23
    - Board Reports, 1961 January 3-1961 February 9 (Box 344)
      On January 30, 1961, Superintendent Jarvis presented communication from the Los Angeles County Counsel regarding American Civil Liberties Union of Southern California, et. al., v. Board of Education of the City of Los Angeles, California Supreme Court, No. LA25788. This communication concerns two recent California Supreme Court majority opinions holding unconstitutional the "Statement of Information" required by the State Legislature of all applicants for civic center permits.
    - Board Reports, 1961 February 14-1961 March 27 (Box 345)
      On March 6, 1961, Mr. J.C. Chambers appeared before the Board and stated, "The California Supereme Court, in a decision which recently became final in the case of the American Civil Liberties Union of Southern California v. Board of Education of the City of Los Angeles, has held to be unconstitutional the Statement of Information for Civic Center applicants as now contained in Section 16565 of the California Education Code, which implements Section 16564."
    - Board Reports, 1961 March 30-1961 May 11 (Box 346)
      On April 6, 1961, the Board adopted the Resolution As To Civic Center Permits.
    - Board Reports, 1961 May 15-1961 June 19 (Box 347)
    - Board Reports, 1961 June 22-1961 July 27 (Box 348)
      At the Annual Meeting on July 3, 1961, Dr. Ralph Richardson was elected Board President for the fiscal year beginning July 1, 1961.
    - Board Reports, 1961 July 31-1961 August 31 (Box 349)
      On August 24, 1961, Board President Richardson shared a letter from Superintendent Jarvis requesting that he be released from his contract as Superintendent of Schools, as of January 1, 1962.
    - Board Reports, 1961 September 5-1961 October 12 (Box 350)
    - Board Reports, 1961 October 16-1961 November 30 (Box 351)
    - Board Reports, 1961 December 4-1962 January 8 (Box 352)
      On January 2, 1962, Jack P. Crowther signed his contract for the Superintendent position and made a statement of acceptance.
    - Board Reports, 1962 January 11-1962 February 21 (Box 353)
    - Board Reports, 1962 February 26-1962 April 2 (Box 354)
    - Board Reports, 1962 April 5-1962 May 14 (Box 355)
    - Board Reports, 1962 May 17-1962 June 21 (Box 356)
      On June 7, 1962, members of the American Civil Liberties Union of Southern California (ACLU), the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), Los Angeles Branch and others addressed the Board on the subject of integration in the Los Angeles City Schools. Board member Hardy's motion for the President to appoint an ad hoc committee of Board members to consider the proposals presented by the ACLU and the NAACP was carried unanimously.
    - Board Reports, 1962 June 25-1962 July 30 (Box 357)
    - Board Reports, 1962 August 2-1962 September 17 (Box 358)
      On September 13, 1962, Superintendent Crowther stated that on Tuesday at Baldwin Hills Elementary School, fifteen children with representatives from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) arrived at the school and asked for admission. The enrollment applications of all students were rejected by the Baldwin Hills School principal when it was determined that the parents had not followed the established procedures of first receiving a transfer permit from the parent school.
      Crowther also reported that a similar procedure was followed at 9 a.m. this morning at Huntington Park High School when fourteen students attempted to enroll without first securing permits from parent schools. Following the Huntington Park High School incident, at 10 a.m., five students attempted to enroll at South Gate High School. Again, their applications were rejected and referred to the parent school.
      On September 17, 1962, Superintendent Crowther read a statement from the NAACP expressing satisfaction that Board of Education is concerned with the problems of schools in which housing conditions create a pattern of segregation and that the school system is attempting to arrive at solutions equitable to all.
    - Board Reports, 1962 September 20-1962 November 5 (Box 359)
    - Board Reports, 1962 November 8-1962 December 27 (Box 360)
    - Board Reports, 1963 January 3-1963 February 14 (Box 361)
      On February 14, 1963, Board member Willett presented a resolution with regard to to the proposed discontinuance of the Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps Program, a part of the Los Angeles City senior high schools since 1919. The resolution urging the United States Congress to direct the Department of Defense to re-allocate funding for the program was carried by 6 members of the Board of Education. President Mary Tinglof indicated that she voted against the resolution as she did not believe in the program.
    - Board Reports, 1963 February 18-1963 March 28 (Box 362)
    - Board Reports, 1963 April 1-1963 May 6 (Box 363)
      On May 2, 1963, Board member Hardy, Chairman of the Ad Hoc Committee to study the question of Equal Educational Opportunities within the District, presented and read an Interim Report with four recommendations that she moved be held until the regular May 16, 1963 Board meeting at which time she would move its adoption.
    - Board Reports, 1963 May 9-1963 June 13 (Box 364)
      On May 20, 1963, the Board discussed the language of the Interim Report of the Ad Hoc Committee on Equal Educational Opportunities in the District. The Board motion that the Superintendent be authorized to prepare rules and regulations for inclusion in the Administrative Guide, was carried unanimously. On June 6, 1963, Board member Richardson moved that the Board request the Superintendent to report whether contractors bidding on school construction are required by Board policies or applicable law to pledge an absence of racial discrimination in the contractors' employment practices. Dr. Richardson's motion was carried unanimously.
    - Board Reports, 1963 June 17-1963 July 22 (Box 365)
      During the July 11, 1963 3:30 p.m. meeting, Mrs. Hardy took the President's chair and on behalf of the Board presented to the outgoing President, Mrs. Mary Tinglof, a gavel hewn from the handrail of the stairs of the old Los Angeles High School.
      During the July 11, 1963 regular meeting, Mr. Jose Montevideo Perez addressed the Board, "Petitioning propria persona under the Constitutional procedure for petitions of grievances and a redress of justice for the resignation of this Board of Education."
      On July 22, 1963, Mrs. Marnesba T. Tackett, Chairman of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People - United Civil Rights Council, addressed the Board and presented a written statement concerning "Failure of the Los Angeles Board of Education to Take Affirmative Action to Alleviate De Facto Segregation in the Public Schools."
    - Board Reports, 1963 July 25-1963 August 29 (Box 366)
      On August 5, 1963, the Board received Summons and Complaint for Declaratory Judgment and Injunction, Order to Show Cause, Plaintiffs' Memorandum of Points and Authorities on Order to Show Cause, Superior Court Action No. 822854, Mary Ellen Crawford, a Minor, by Ellen Crawford, her Guardian Ad Litem; et al, Plaintiffs, vs. Board of Education of the City of Los Angeles, Defendant, asking judgment requiring Board to correct racial imbalance at Jordan High School.
      On August 8, 1963, Robert B. Young of the Citizen Resource Group working with the Board's Ad Hoc Committee, read a letter of concern regarding statements made by members of the Board of Education indicating that they still interpret Board policy as being against segregation but not for integration.
      On August 8, 1963, speakers from the NAACP, the UCRC, Congress of Racial Equality, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee, and Los Angeles County Commission on Human Relations addressed the Board on the subject of de facto segregation in District schools. Later, Board member Arthur Gardner read a statement of concession on faculty racial imbalance and de facto segregation within the schools and Board member Charles Reed Smoot read a statement which compared Board member Mary Tinglof's social policies and those of the NAACP and the ACLU as "vicious" and "totalitarian."
      On August 12, 1963, Tinglof responded to Smoot, "This wave of indignation has been brought about by our own shortsightedness, whether in Birmingham or Los Angeles, and I shall ride that crest so long as some Americans continue to wear blinders on Justice for all."
      On August 15, 1963, President Hardy presented Recommendations to the Board submitted by Dr. Francisco Bravo at the Mexican-American Education Conference held on August 9, 1963.
    - Board Reports, 1963 September 5-1963 October 17 (Box 367)
      On September 12, 1963, the Ad Hoc Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity submitted its report to the Board. Committee members included Chairman Georgiana Hardy, Arthur F. Gardner and Hugh C. Willett.
      On September 16, 1963, Board member Smoot read a letter from Kenneth B. Fry, Chairman, Education Committee, Los Angeles Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) that asked for the resignation or dismissal of Associate Superintendent Robert E. Kelly based on his recent statements to the Los Angeles Times on September 7, 1963, "Preponderance of one race (at a school) is not harmful to school children."
      Board member Smoot made a statement against Fry and CORE and made a motion of public support for the Associate Superintendent. President Hardy declared the motion carried with 6 ayes and one abstention from Board member Tinglof.
      On October 3, 7, 10 and 17, 1963, the Board discussed the postponed motion to adopt the Report of the Ad Hoc Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity.
      On October 14, 1963, Board member Chambers moved that the Board call on CORE to retract the following untrue statements contained in a bulletin circulated by CORE at many Los Angeles City Schools on October 10, 1963, "The Los Angeles Board of Education says 'Segregate'...For too long the Board has been herding vast numbers of Negroes and Mexicans into inadequate, overcrowded, segregated schools."
    - Board Reports, 1963 October 21-1963 November 26 (Box 368)
      On October 24, 1963, President Hardy presented and read a statement regarding the Congress Of Racial Equality (CORE) demonstrations over "racial issues" which included marches, sit-ins and study-ins in the Board of Education halls.
      On October 31, 1963, the Board discussed the September 19, 1963 march to the Board organized by CORE, allegations against administrators who locked the gates and doors of Jordan High School to prevent students from leaving and the presence of police on or near this campus.
      On November 18, 1963, a group of approximately forty representatives from the Los Angeles CORE began singing while President Hardy called for order without success. Hardy read Education Code Section 16701 regarding willful disturbance of a public school meeting as a misdemeanor while the group continued the "loud singing" until the meeting was adjourned due to the disturbance.
      On November 21, 1963, Board member Richardson moved to seek an injunction against CORE and that the Superintendent be authorized to direct Security Officers to place participants of future disruptions of Board meetings under arrest. The motion was passed with 6 ayes and an abstention from Mrs. Tinglof.
    - Board Reports, 1963 November 27-1963 December 30 (Box 369)
      On December 23, 1963, a special meeting was held for additional motions and discussions concerning the Ad Hoc Committee Report.
    - Board Reports, 1964 January 2-1964 February 10 (Box 370)
      On January 9, 1964, the Board received a copy of Resolution No. 4878 adopted by the City Council of the City of Huntington Park protesting the recent changes in school attendance area boundaries within the city of Huntington Park and requesting the Board re-establish its policy of permitting students who reside in Huntington Park to attend public schools located in Huntington Park.
    - Board Reports, 1964 February 13-1964 March 16 (Box 371)
    - Board Reports, 1964 March 19-1964 April 23 (Box 372)
    - Board Reports, 1964 April 30-1964 June 1 (Box 373)
      On May 14, 1964, President Hardy acknowledged the tenth anniversary of the May 17, 1954 decision of the United States Supreme Court in the historic case of Brown v. Board of Education and stated, "While the Los Angeles City School Districts have not imposed racial segregation on their students, the Brown case and the public actions and expressions which followed have stirred this Board and the community to undertake broad programs of action to eliminate discrimination wherever found, and to ensure that equality of educational opportunity is provided for all pupils in our schools, regardless of race or socio-economic conditions."
    - Board Reports, 1964 June 4-1964 July 9 (Box 374)
    - Board Reports, 1964 July 13-1964 August 13 (Box 375)
    - Board Reports, 1964 August 17-1964 September 28 (Box 376)
    - Board Reports, 1964 October 1-1964 November 12 (Box 377)
      The October 22, 1964 2:00 p.m. Minutes include an informative report to the Board from the Division of Secondary Education entitled The Adjustment Center School "Another Opportunity." Adjustment center high schools is a title designating those institutions enrolling students whose emotional, behavior, or concomitant learning problems are of such serious nature and complexity that regular schools are unable to adequately cope with them. The title adjustment center school was officially adopted as a result of Board action on April 24, 1961.
    - Board Reports, 1964 November 16-1964 December 31 (Box 378)
    - Board Reports, 1965 January 4-1965 February 4 (Box 379)
    - Board Reports, 1965 February 8-1965 March 11 (Box 380)
      On February 18, 1965, the Board amended its proposed Teacher Transfer Policy so that requests for transfers of permanent teachers be granted at the earliest possible date.
    - Board Reports, 1965 March 15-1965 April 15 (Box 381)
    - Board Reports, 1965 April 19-1965 May 20 (Box 382)
    - Board Reports, 1965 May 24-1965 June 21 (Box 383)
    - Board Reports, 1965 June 24-1965 July 22 (Box 384)
    - Board Reports, 1965 July 26-1965 August 30 (Box 385)
      On August 16, 1965, Superintendent Crowther reported that school buses continue to transport the National Guard to the southeast section of the School District and 18 schools are in use as centers of the National Guard. Crowther also reported that at a morning meeting with a member of Governor Brown's staff, it was determined that the Los Angeles City Schools will not be involved in the community feeding problem if the situation does not worsen. Additionally, Crowther stated that as an aftermath of this emergency the District is receiving requests for transfer from school personnel and as a result, a staffing problem may develop near the opening of school.
    - Board Reports, 1965 September 2-1965 October 4 (Box 386)
    - Board Reports, 1965 October 7-1965 November 10 (Box 387)
    - Board Reports, 1965 November 15-1965 December 30 (Box 388)
    - Board Reports, 1966 January 3-1966 February 7 (Box 389)
    - Board Reports, 1966 February 10-1966 March 14 (Box 390)
      On February 10, 1966, the Reverend Mr. James Hargett addressed the Board on the subject: "Does Separate Education Plus Compensation Equal Integrated Education?" Hargett expressed concern that there had not been serious debate about the school system's concern for integration and its relationship to the 1966 Bond Issue.
    - Board Reports, 1966 March 17-1966 April 14 (Box 391)
    - Board Reports, 1966 April 18-1966 May 16 (Box 392)
      On May 5, 1966, the Reverend James E. Jones moved the adoption of a resolution to relieve overcrowding in disadvantaged areas by making use of schools with unused classroom facilities and allowing students intra-district transfers to schools with available classroom space under the Board's "Open School" plan. President Richardson declared the motion failed for lack of four affirmative votes.
    - Board Reports, 1966 May 19-1966 June 13 (Box 393)
      On May 26, 1966, Mrs. Hardy moved that the Reverend James E. Jones be directed to attend the White House conference "To Fulfill These Rights," on request of the President of the United States, to be held on June 1 through June 2, 1966 in Washington D.C.. The motion was carried unanimously.
    - Board Reports, 1966 June 20-1966 July 11 (Box 394)
    - Board Reports, 1966 July 14-1966 August 15 (Box 395)
    - Board Reports, 1966 August 18-1966 September 26 (Box 396)
      On September 15, 1966, the Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Member of Congress, addressed the Board concerning the development and implementation of the Compensatory Education Program in the Los Angeles City Schools. Hawkins stated that he believed there was de facto segregation in the Los Angeles City Schools, that the Board was not complying with Title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 and urged the Board to take action to correct this situation.
    - Board Reports, 1966 September 29-1966 November 7 (Box 397)
    - Board Reports, 1966 November 10-1966 December 12 (Box 398)
    - Board Reports, 1966 December 15-1966 December 29 (Box 399)
    - Board Reports, 1967 January 3-1967 January 30 (Box 400)
    - Board Reports, 1967 February 2-1967 March 2 (Box 401)
    - Board Reports, 1967 March 6-1967 April 3 (Box 402)
    - Board Reports, 1967 April 6-1967 May 1 (Box 403)
    - Board Reports, 1967 May 4-1967 May 22 (Box 404)
    - Board Reports, 1967 May 25-1967 June 19 (Box 405)
    - Board Reports, 1967 June 22-1967 July 13 (Box 406)
      On July 3, 1967, the City Clerk of Los Angeles certified the re-election of J.C. Chambers, Georgiana Hardy, Arthur F. Gardner and the election of Julian Nava as members of the Board of Education. Georgiana Hardy was elected President for the fiscal year beginning July 1, 1967. On July 6, 1967, the Reverend Mr. Jones moved that the Board set as its goal a policy of complete desegregation and work toward this goal at all levels and divisions of the system, and further that the staff be directed to devise and execute such plans as rapidly as possible. The President declared the motion carried.
    - Board Reports, 1967 July 17-1967 August 14 (Box 407)
    - Board Reports, 1967 August 17-1967 September 18 (Box 408)
    - Board Reports, 1967 September 21-1967 October 19 (Box 409)
    - Board Reports, 1967 October 23-1967 November 13 (Box 410)
      On October 23, 1967, the Board approved a statement concerning a situation at Manual Arts High School. Dr. Richardson presented the statement that the Board is seeking court action to establish and maintain order at Manual Arts High School, that Principal Robert Denahy remain at Manual Arts at least until the end of the semester, that the faculty return to duty on Tuesday morning, and that the Board pledges to provide all possible funds and staff necessary to achieve improved education at Manual Arts High School.
    - Board Reports, 1967 November 16-1967 December 11 (Box 411)
    - Board Reports, 1967 December 14-1967 December 28 (Box 412)
      On December 21, 1967, the Reverend Mr. Jones read a prepared statement about segregation, disparities in education as a result of racial isolation and presented a statement of policy intent to eliminate de facto segregation in the Los Angeles School System. The Reverend Mr. Jones moved that the Board reaffirm Directive No. 1 of the Ad Hoc Committee Report of 1963. Said motion was seconded by Dr. Nava and carried following discussion.
    - Board Reports, 1968 January 2-1968 January 25 (Box 413)
    - Board Reports, 1968 January 29-1968 February 21 (Box 414)
    - Board Reports, 1968 February 26-1968 March 21 (Box 415)
      On February 26, 1968, Superintendent Crowther presented a twenty page statement entitled: "First Informative Progress Report On District Integration Policy To The Los Angeles City Board of Education." President Hardy stated that there would be no action taken to implement the Superintendent's report until after the Board had time to study it in depth.
      On March 7, 1968, Mr. Thomas Reddin, Chief of Police, Los Angeles Police Department addressed the Board and discussed student walk outs and school disturbances at various Los Angeles City Schools. Dr. Nava presented a request from student representatives of various high schools that members of the Board meet with them at Abraham Lincoln High School at 10 a.m. on March 8, 1968 to discuss student problems.
      During the March 11, 1968 Special Meeting at 3:00 p.m., students and faculty including Sal Castro, from eight high schools including Garfield, Lincoln, Wilson, Belmont, Roosevelt, Jefferson, Hamilton and Marshall addressed the Board concerning student unrest.
    - Board Reports, 1968 March 25-1968 April 15 (Box 416)
      During a Special Meeting on March 26, 1968 at 4:00 p.m., in the auditorium of Abraham Lincoln High School, Mr. Sal Castro, Adviser of the Blow-out Committee introduced Blow-out representatives from Garfield, Lincoln, Roosevelt and Wilson High Schools and Chairman Mr. Vahac Mardirosian of the Educational Issues Coordinating Committee to give presentations and open discussion with the Board regarding the East Los Angeles student walkouts.
      These Meeting Minutes also contain a document from Superintendent Crowther entitled "Staff Response to Demands and Requests Presented in Connection With Student Walkouts."
    - Board Reports, 1968 April 18-1968 May 9 (Box 417)
    - Board Reports, 1968 May 13-1968 June 6 (Box 418)
    - Board Reports, 1968 June 10-1968 June 27 (Box 419)
    - Board Reports, 1968 July 1-1968 July 29 (Box 420)
      On July 1, 1968, newly elected Board President James E. Jones referred to this Board's custom of opening the first meeting of each month with a prayer of invocation and introduced the Reverend Ray Pedrotti, First United Presbyterian Church, Los Angeles, who delivered the prayer of invocation.
      On July 18, 1968, the Reverend Vahac Mardirosian, Chairman, Educational Issues Coordinating Committee, addressed the Board expressing concern for the large dropout rate among Mexican American high school students and stating that the high schools are not adequately preparing students to enter college. Following discussion, Dr. Richardson's motion that the Chairman of the Committee on Urban Affairs convene a meeting of this committee to meet with Reverend Mardirosian was carried unanimously.
    - Board Reports, 1968 August 1-1968 August 26 (Box 421)
      On August 26, 1968, Mr. Frederick J. Dumas, representing the Council of Black Administrators (COBA), addressed the Board and announced the organization of the Council concerned with the resolution of educational problems of the Black community. Mr. Dumas offered the Council's services of to the Board and presented its statement of purpose and objectives.
    - Board Reports, 1968 August 29-1968 September 19 (Box 422)